<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ's first sermon, or, The absolute necessity, gospel duty, and Christian practice of repentance, opened and applied, by a godly, able, and faithful minister of Jesus Christ. ; Wherein is discovered, what repentance is, as also the great necessity thereof to salvation: with the great folly and desperate madness of all those that delay and put off repentance unto a sick bed, or old age. ; Together with the great benefit, joy, and comfort that shall be to the souls of all those that timely and truly repent.</title>
            <author>Hart, John, D.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077505</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077505</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151567</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87175)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151567)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2265:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ's first sermon, or, The absolute necessity, gospel duty, and Christian practice of repentance, opened and applied, by a godly, able, and faithful minister of Jesus Christ. ; Wherein is discovered, what repentance is, as also the great necessity thereof to salvation: with the great folly and desperate madness of all those that delay and put off repentance unto a sick bed, or old age. ; Together with the great benefit, joy, and comfort that shall be to the souls of all those that timely and truly repent.</title>
                  <author>Hart, John, D.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The eleventh edition, with many additions.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Eliz. Andrews, at the White Lion near Pye-Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Hart by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [46].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College Library, Dublin, Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151567:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſts Firſt SERMON, OR The abſolute neceſſity, Goſpel Duty, and Chriſtian Practice of Repentance, Opened and Applied, by a godly, able, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Wherein is diſcovered, what Repentance is; as alſo the great neceſſity thereof to ſalvation: with the great folly and deſperate madneſs of all thoſe that delay and put off their Repentance unto a Sick Bed, or Old Age.</p>
            <p>Together with the great Benefit, Joy, and Comfort that ſhall be to the Souls of all thoſe that timely and truly Repent.</p>
            <p>The eleventh Edition, with many Additions.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 4.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>From that time Jeſus began to preach, and to ſay, Repent, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 13.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Except ye Repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Eliz. Andrews,</hi> at the White Lion near <hi>Pye-Corner.</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:151567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Chriſts firſt Sermon. OR, The abſolute neceſſity, duty, and Chriſtian Practice of REPENTANCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Acts 17.30, 31.</bibl>
                  <p>The times of this ignorance God winked at, but now commandeth all men every where to repent: Becauſe he hath appointed a Day, in which he will judge the world in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouneſs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Bleſſed Apoſtle Saint Paul in theſe words, beloved, endeavours to take off the ſuperſtitious Athenians from their Idolatry and worſhipping of falſe gods; gods of ſilver and gold, which indeed are no gods, but the work of mens hands; and this he doth, firſt, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to convince them of the folly of their Idolatry; and then ſecondly, in laying before them the power and goodneſs of God,
<pb facs="tcp:151567:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>in making and preſerving the world, and all things therein. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verſes) <hi>made the world, and all things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and is Lord over all, and gives to all life, and breath, and all things; and in him we all live, and move, and have our being: and it is he that hath ſet the bounds of our habitations.</hi> Therefore (ſaith he) you need not think that the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head is like unto gold, or ſilver, or ſtones, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by art or mans devices; for God is Lord both of heaven and earth. I but ſay theſe Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, (like ſome now adayes) we did as our fore-fathers did, they ſhorſhipped ſuch gods as theſe, &amp; were of the ſame Religion as our fore-fathers were. But ſaith the Apoſtle, this was done in ignorance, and the times of this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance God winked at; your fore-fathers had not the light of the Goſpel, they never heard of Jeſus Chriſt: But now, ſaith he, Chriſt is preached, &amp; the light of the Goſpel ſhines forth in the world, therefore now ye muſt repent, and turn from theſe idols, and ſerve the living God. Now God commands all men every where to repent, although God in times paſt ſuffered all Nations to walk in their own wayes: Now hath he ſent us to preach Chriſt unto you, that you should turn from theſe vanities, and ſerve the living God. If your fore-fathers ſinned, it was through their ignorance and want of the
<pb facs="tcp:151567:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt: but if you ſin and go on in your idolatry, it is through wilfulnes, and God will be revenged on you. In the words you may obſerve theſe four things; firſt, a duty commanded, and that is repentance; ſecondly, the commander, &amp; that is God, <hi>God command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> thirdly, the perſons to whom this command is enjoyned, and that is all men, every where, high and low, rich and poor, all the world over; fourthly and laſtly, the time when, and that is now; now God commandeth all men every where to repent, now in theſe times of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: <hi>To day if you will hear my voice,</hi> ſaith God in <hi>Pſalm 95.7.</hi> From the worlds thus opened, I ſhall give you theſe four pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tical obſervations: The firſt is this, that Repentance is a needful and neceſſary duty commanded by God. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that every man &amp; woman in the world is bound to repent. Thirdly, that the doctrine of the Goſpel is a doctrine of Repentance: It was Chriſts firſt Sermon, as you may ſée, <hi>Mat. 4.16. Jeſus began to preach, and to ſay, Repent.</hi> Fourthly and laſtly, obſerve from theſe words that God expects more, and looks for more from men under the Goſpel, then from thoſe who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of the Goſpel. Theſe four obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are all of them very clear from the words of the test, I ſhall only therefore give you ſome few futher proofs of them from Scripture, and
<pb facs="tcp:151567:4"/>ſo proceed in the opening and handling of the two firſt obſervations, and from thence I ſhall draw ſundry practical uſes, which I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by Gods aſſiſtance, to apply home unto your ſouls, I ſhall therefore joyn the two firſt obſervations into one intire propoſition, thus. That repentance is a needful and neceſſary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty commanded by God, and that every man and woman in the world is bound to repent. <hi>Except ye repent</hi> (ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luke 13. 3) ye ſhall all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> And <hi>2 Per. 3.9. God is not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. As I live</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ezek. 33.11.) I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live. Turn ye, turn ye from your evil wayes; for why will ye die, O houſe of Iſrael.</hi> And in <hi>Mat. 3.2. Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is at hand.</hi> And ſo likewiſe in <hi>Act 2.38. Repent &amp; be baptized every one of you in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of ſins</hi> Repentance is needful for all, there are none ſo wiſe, none ſo learned, none ſo holy, but ſtand in néed of repentance. <hi>In many things</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>James) we ſin all, Jam, 3.2.</hi> And in <hi>Rom. 3.23. All have ſinned.</hi> Young ones have ſinned, and therefore have need to repent, &amp; that betimes, leſt as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Heb. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. Through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of ſin their hearts be hardned.</hi> Its good for young ones, yea its the beſt courſe they can
<pb facs="tcp:151567:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>take, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ. 12.1. To remember their Creator in the dayes of their youth;</hi> and not to put off repentance unto old age, or the death-bed, for then it may be too late: For although true repentance is never too late, yet late repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is ſeldom true. It is a good obſervation of a holy man; ſaith he, ſpeaking of the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Thief, <hi>God ſaved one at the laſt hour, that none might deſpair, and but one, that none might preſume.</hi> Thou that wilt not repent when thou maiſt, it may be God will not give thée time to repent hereafter when thou wouldeſt: Doeſt thou think to do that in thy old age, which thou wilt not do in thy youth? Canſt thou do that in one hour on thy death-bed, which thou art not able to do ſufficiently all thy life time; And then likewiſe old men have néed of repentance, they have lived a long time in ſin, and have long enough, yea, too too long neglected repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: Young men may dye ſoon, but old men cannot live long; therefore both young and old have néed to repent, that they may receive the remiſſion of their ſins, <hi>Mark 1, 4.</hi> And for your better underſtanding of this great &amp; neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry duty of repentance. I ſhall little ſhew you what it is, and that briefly. Repentance is of two ſorts, either real or unfeigned, or elſe ſéem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hypocritical; ſéeming repentance that's common to wicked men, and is altogether Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal
<pb facs="tcp:151567:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ariſing from the accuſations of their own conſciences, ſuch a repentance, as this, was that of <hi>Judas;</hi> and then there is a real and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance, which doth properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the godly, and this is likewiſe of two ſorts; Legal and Evangelical: Legal repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that comes from the Law, giving us the ſight of our ſins and our miſery by ſin; the Law is our School-maſter to bring us to Chriſt, <hi>Gal. 3.24.</hi> But Evangelical repentance that ſprings from faith in Chriſt, and carries out the ſoul unto Chriſt in oppoſition to every ſin, and to a forſaking of every evil way: repentance then I ſhall thus deſcribe, I ſay repentance is a gift of God by which a believing ſinner being caſt down in the ſight and ſenſe of his own ſinnes, doth utterly forſake and abhor all his former evil wayes, and turns to the Lord with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart.</p>
            <p>I ſay it is a gift of God, that which comes from God and not from nature, its a flower ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver grew in natures garden; neither birth nor bréeding, neither art nor learning, nor any other ſublunarypower or qualification, is able to beget repentance: true repentance comes from above. <hi>Every good and perfect gift</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>James) comes from above, Jam. 1.17.</hi> Grace doth not grow here below, but comes down from the father of lights. The Apoſtles, <hi>Acts
<pb facs="tcp:151567:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>11.18. glorified God, that to the Gentiles he had granted repentance unto life.</hi> Repentance is the quickning of a dead ſoul, and therefore muſt be the act of him who is the giver of all life. <hi>We are all of us by nature dead in ſins and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes Epheſ.</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> and the <hi>1.</hi> A man by nature is no more able to perform an act of true grace, then a dead perſon in the grave is able to do an act of nature. <hi>They that live in ſin</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the widow that lives in pleaſure, <hi>1 Tim. 5.6.) are dead while they live. Repentance then is the gift of God, Acts 11.18. God granted repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto life.</hi> So in <hi>1 Tim. 2.25.</hi> the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God are required to inſtruct thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, with méekneſs; if God peradventure wil give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth, that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves out of the ſnares of the devil. It is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>Acts 5.31 He is exalted to be a Prince and a Saviour, to give repentance unto Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> Faith and repentance are ſupernatural works, &amp; we may as wel create new heavens and a new earth, as do theſe acts of our ſelves; it is God alone that works them in our hearts by the efficacious operations of his Spirit. <hi>2 Cor. 3.5. We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves but it is God that worketh in us both to will and to do, of his good pleaſure, Phil 2.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151567:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Secondly, repentance is a change, firſt of the heart, then of the whole man: there muſt be a new heart, and a new hand; a new life, and a new head: all things muſt be new where re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is. <hi>If any man be in Chriſt</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>he is a new creature, 1 Cor. 5.17.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance makes a man a new man, and it is only in the power of God to renew our hearts, neither Angels nor men are able to do it. In <hi>Jer. 31.18, 19. ſaith Ephraim, Turn thou me, and I ſhal be turned, for thou art the Lord my God, Surely after that I was turned I repented, and after that I was inſtructed, I ſmote upon my thigh, I was aſhamed, yea even confounded, becauſe I did bear the reproach of my youth.</hi> Here is the character of a true repentance, it is the Lord that muſt change our hearts, it is he only that muſt give us new hearts, and take from us theſe hearts of ſtone: it is the Lord that muſt pluck us out of the ſnares of the Devil, and caſt down the ſtrong holds of ſin in us, if God do not turn us, we ſhall never be turned. <hi>After that I was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I repented ſaith Ephraim.</hi> But I proceed in the deſcription of repentance.</p>
            <p>Its a gift of God, I ſay whereby a believing ſinner turns from all his ſins unto God; I ſay, a believing ſinner, becauſe faith muſt firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede and go before repentance, for none can tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent, but he muſt firſt believe: there may
<pb facs="tcp:151567:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>be in a ſinner that which we call Legal repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which may cauſe a ſinner to fall out with his ſins, &amp; it may be to loath them with a kinde of deteſtation: its poſſible a wicked man may repent that ever he knew what ſin meant, or that ever he had to do with ſin; all this may be, and yet no true repentance, becauſe no true faith, for true repentance cauſes a hatred of ſin, as it is diſpleaſing to God, aſwell as hurtful to our ſelves; yea, he hates ſin as hell, yea worſe then hell it ſelf, which cannot be in an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving ſoul. It cannot be denied but that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is a ſaving grace; and if ſo, then none can partake of this ſaving grace, till he be firſt united unto Chriſt the fountain of all grace: ſo then faith muſt needs be before repentance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, where true repentance is, there is a change wrought in the whole man, and a tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, firſt, to our ſelves: ſecondly, to God: and thirdly to man. An unrepentant ſinner is out of himſelf; and he is not onely out of his way, but out of his wits. In <hi>Luke 15.17.</hi> when the Prodigal came to himſelf, he ſaid; <hi>Father I have ſinned;</hi> this is the firſt ſtep to repentance, ſelf-returning. Secondly, repentance is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to God, <hi>If thou wilt return O Iſrael, ſaith the Lord, return unto me, Jer. 4.1.</hi> The grace of repentance is ſuitably expreſſed by this act of returning to God, &amp; they who did not repent,
<pb facs="tcp:151567:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>are ſaid not to return to God. In <hi>Amos.</hi> 4 1. God ſaith, <hi>Notwithſtanding I have given you cleanneſs of teeth, and want of bread, yet have you not returned; notwithſtanding I have with-holden the rain from you, and ſmitten you with blaſtings and mildew, and ſent among you the Peſtilence: Notwithſtanding I have ſlain your young men by the ſword, and overthrown ſome of you as I over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw Sodom and Gomorrah, by fire; yet have you not returned unto me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is a turning from ſin to God: <hi>Sin turns men from God, and draws the ſoul into the wayes of death, Jam.</hi> 1.14. A man is drawn away of his own luſts and enticed, drawn away from God and from the truth of God: but when once Repentance comes, he turns back again, he changes his minde then, and abhors himſelf for what he hath done, <hi>Job 42.6. I abhor my ſelf, and repent</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>in duſt and aſhes.</hi> The prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal was drawn away from his fathers houſe through his own luſts, and yet at laſt he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed firſt to himſelf, ſecondly to his father, <hi>Luke 15 17. When he came to himſelf he ſaid I wil ariſe and go to my father, and ſay unto him, Father, I have ſinned againſt heaven and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinners are ſaid to be mad, but repentance brings men to their right wits again: chery impenitent ſinner is a mad men, a meet Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;
<pb facs="tcp:151567:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>who but a mad man will run himſelf wilfully into the fire, as every wicked man doth, he runs headlong to deſtruction; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance turns men from this madneſs. In <hi>Acts</hi> 16.18. it is called, <hi>A turning of men from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</hi> Sin is a darkneſs, and when men ſin they know not what they do; but Repentance enlightens men, and ſets them at liberty. In <hi>Acts</hi> 20.20. Repentances &amp; turning to God are put together, they are one and the ſame, the one cannot be without the other; but it is not any turning that doth this, but it is a turning of the judgemant, and a turning of the will and affections: ſo that men that are turned, are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried wholly from ſin and wickedneſs, unto God, <hi>Joel 3.12. Turn unto me</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>with all your heart:</hi> If it be with a piece, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth, it is altogether deceitful.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Repentance is a returning to men; we muſt not be aſhamed to acknowledge our faults one to another, <hi>Jam. 5.16. Confeſs your faults one to another, and pray one for another.</hi> If we have dene any man wrong, we ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it. Is it ſo then that Repentance flowes from Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and turns men from ſin unto God, then I obſerve, that there are many in the world, who as yet never knew what true repentance meaneth, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:151567:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are yet in unbelief &amp; without faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there can be no repentance: Men may cry bitterly, and humble themſelves in ſackcloth and aſhes, as <hi>Ahab</hi> did: men may have the hort ours of Hell in their conſciences as <hi>Judas</hi> had; Men may reform many things that are amiſs, as <hi>Herod</hi> did, and yet being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belicvers, they are ſtill in the eſtate of impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency: It is an infallible demonſtration, that they never yet truly taſted of the love of God in the pardon of their ſins, who dare preſume to take a liberty to ſin, or delight themſelves in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſin whatſoever; they that truly believe, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, dare not allow themſelves in any ſin: for as faith purifies the heart, ſo faith &amp; repentance keeps the heart pure, and makes the conſcience tender: and the more pure the heart is, the more will it abſtain from all things that are evil.</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, is Repentance the gift and grace of God, whereby a believing ſinner being humbled under the ſight and ſenſe of his ſins, doth truly turn to God. Then we may obſerve, that where true repentance is, there is alſo hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for ſin. It is not poſſible that ever any ſoul ſhould truly repent, that is not truly humbled and caſt down in the ſight &amp; ſenſe of his ſins. <hi>Turn unto me</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>with all your heart, with faſting, with weeping, and with mourning, Joel 2.12.</hi> The <hi>Ninivites</hi> when they
<pb facs="tcp:151567:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>repented, they humbled themſelves from the higheſt to the loweſt; and this alſo ſhews us, that the greateſt part of men and women in the world never yet truly repented, becauſe they were never yet truly humbled: IT is not every kinde of ſorrow that works repentance, but as it is in 2 <hi>Cor 7.10. Onely goldy ſorrow worketh repentance never to be repented of.</hi> And as there may be a counterfeit repentance, ſo there may be a counterfiet humiliation: The ſignes and marks of true humiliation are theſe, Firſt, the ſoul that is truly humbled for ſin, is very free in confeſſion of ſin; and the Scriptures tell us, that thoſe that have been moſt humbled for ſin, have bin freeſt in the confeſſion of their ſins: as <hi>David, Nehemiah, Job,</hi> and others, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.3. ſaith <hi>David, I acknowledg my tranſgreſſion, and my ſin is ever before me.</hi> And this confeſſion of ſin, will be in ſome meaſure ſuitable to our humiliation; if our ſorrow for ſin be ſincere, our confeſſion will be ſo too: Therefore all thoſe who are leſs afraid to commit ſin then they are aſhamed to confeſs ſin; were never yet truly humbled for ſin, neither ſhall their ſouls reap any ben fit by it. <hi>Prov. 28.13. He that covereth his ſins ſhall not proſper, but whoſo confeſſeth and forſaketh them ſhall finde mercy.</hi> They that will not finde out their ſins to confeſs them, to be ſure, one day or other their ſins ſhall finde them
<pb facs="tcp:151567:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>out to forment them: if ſin finde us not out in youth, it will finde us out in age; if it finde us not out in health, yet it will find us out in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; if it finde us not out in life, yet it will finde us out in death; if it finde us not out in death, yet it will finde us out after death in the day of judgement: either one time or other out ſins will finde us out. <hi>Numb. 25., 33. Your ſins</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>ſhall finde you out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, godly ſorrow and humiliation for ſin, cauſeth the ſoul that is humbled utterly to loath, and abhor, and hate ſin: <hi>Ezek. 20.43. Ye ſhall remember your ways and your doings where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you have been defiled, and ye ſhall loath your ſelves in your own ſight, for all your evil that you have committed.</hi> Sin is odious and hateful to an humble ſoul: <hi>I abhor every falſe way, (ſaith David) Rivers of tears run down mine eyes, becauſe men keep not thy law, Pſal. 119.164.136.</hi> Nature may teach a man to loath ſin in others, but its onely grace that teaches us to abhor ſin in out ſelves, When <hi>Judab, Gen. 38.24.</hi> heard that his daughter <hi>Thanmar</hi> had played the harlot, he preſently caſt ſentence of death upon her; <hi>Bring her forth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſhe may be burned:</hi> But when he ſaw by the pledges that ſin was his own, <hi>Judah</hi> was then ſilent, no more talk of burning her then. A ſoul truly humbled, will hate ſin whereſoever it is; eſpecially in his own
<pb facs="tcp:151567:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>boſom; men will flie from venomous and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful creatures whereſoever they are, eſpecially if they be near them, becauſe they are then in moſt danger to be hurt by them; all the ſins of the world cannot do a ſoul ſo much hurt as his own ſins; then they that do not hate ſin in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are not truly humbled for ſin.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he that is truly humbled, is willing to take ſhame to himſelf, the humble ſinner is willing to be aſhamed of his folly: <hi>Ezek. 16. 63. That thou mayeſt remember and be aſhamed, and never open thy mouth more, when I am pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified towards thee for all that thou haſt done,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, a truly humble ſoul will be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive the word of God with all readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: what's the reaſon men are no more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for ſin; Surely this, becauſe they deſpiſe or neglect the good, word of God, which is the onely means to get humility: the humble peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſoul, is the moſt tractable and teachable ſoul in the world, and he above all other is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to embrace the word of God.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, a true humble ſoul is ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to put in practiſe all theſe duties which he hath formerly learned out of the word of God: When <hi>Paul</hi> was once truly humbled, he confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not any longer with fleſh and blood, but laying aſide all carnal reaſonings, goes on tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly
<pb facs="tcp:151567:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>in his work of preaching the Goſpel, <hi>Gal. 1.16.</hi> Thus you mayſee that where true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is, there is alſo a true humiliation and ſorrow for ſin; then every one learn to be humble and that betimes: for as women the longer they are ere they bring forth children the harder is their labour; even ſo, they that put off repentance to old age, muſt expect the ſorer tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. Lamentably are they miſtaken, who put off their repentance to their old age: is it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the pains and weakneſs of old age will be any advantage or eaſe to thy repentance. <hi>Rev. 16.19.</hi> its ſaid, <hi>that at the pouring forth of the fourth viol, when God ſmote the inhabitants of the earth with a ſcorching heat, that they blaſphemed the name of God and repented not.</hi> Its a woful thing to put off repentance to a pained body, or to a ſick bed: pain in its own nature fits rather to blaſpheme, and turn from God, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to God; and its very common that ſick perſons either repent not at all, or if they do, at the beſt their repentance is but a ſickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: ſickneſs doth only abate and reſtrain the power of mens luſts, it never deſtroyes the life of ſin, death it ſelf cannot kill ſin; wicked mens ſins live when they are dead, the grave cannot conſume them, nor the fire of hell: the ſins of unbelievers remain not onely in their guilt, but in their power to all eternity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151567:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Is it ſo then, that repentance is a turning from ſin unto God, then I obſerve, that there can be no true repentance where ſin is delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in: he that lives in the love &amp; practice of any ſin knoweth not what repentance meaneth, for repentance takes off the heart from the love of ſin, and works it to ſuch a diſlike of ſin, that it abhors the very occaſion of ſin; if ſin comes and tells a gracion penitent ſoul of the profits and pleaſures of ſin, O ſaith a gracions heart, the ſweetneſs will prove bitterneſs in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end. True repentance takes off the heart from all ſin, as well ſmall as great, not from ſome few ſins, but from all ſin; for he that turns not from all, turns from none in truth: and it is not enough to turn from all ſin, but we muſt turn from the commands of ſin and ſatan unto the commands of God; from worldlineſs, to heavenly mindedneſs; from pride to humility; from hatred and envy, to love: the Tree that bears not good fruit will be hewen down and eaſt into the fire, as well as the trée that bears ill fruit. I beſéech ye therefore brethren in the bowels of mercy, for the Lords ſake I intreat every one of you that deſire to be ſaved, that you would turn away from all your iniquities, and that ſpéedily, leſt your repentance be too late: And to this end, be earneſt with God by prayer, for the aſſiſtance of his ſpirit in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing
<pb facs="tcp:151567:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>of thy ſins, and caſt thy ſelt wholly upon the Lord.</p>
            <p>Chery true Penitent is wholly the Lords, the diſire of his ſoul is to God, and to the remembrance of his name; with his ſoul he deſires God in the night, and with his Spirit within him, he ſeeketh the Lord in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Iſa. 26.8, 9.</hi> He is now a conſtant ſuiter at the throne of grace, and with full purpoſe of heart he cleaves to God, and loves the place where his honour dwells, <hi>Pſalm 26.8.</hi> All his deſire is to know more of God, and how he may love him more and ſerve him better; the ſervice and ſervants of God, how joyful are they to his ſoul? He takes all opportunities of doing good, he keeps his heart with all diligence, and the <hi>door of his lips that he offend not with his tongue, Pſalm 39.1.</hi> His heart is enſlamed with the love of God, that he endeavours with all his might to ſhew forth the praiſes of the Lord. By which it appears, that a turning to God, is not barely a turning from ſin, but a practiſing of good, and a walking up rightly before the Lord in all well-pleaſing, all out dayes.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo then that repentance is needful and abſolutely neceſſary for all perſons; in what a ſad condition then are the greateſt part of men and women in the world, who as yet are as far from true repentance as light is from darknes,
<pb facs="tcp:151567:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>and yet poor ſouls, they ſmooth themſelves up with this conceit, that God is merciful, &amp; they hope to be ſaved as wel as the beſt, &amp; they thank God all is well with them; and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they never repented of their ſins: true repentance is a Grace almoſt out of faſhion in theſe ſelf-conceited times, wherin mens minds are ſo much running after novelties and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward formalities; but the power of holineſs, and the doctrine' of repentance and ſelf-mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, theſe are not minded; nay, by many are accounted Legal, and altogether needleſs.</p>
            <p>There are three ſorts of people that I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak of in the uſe of this Point: and the firſt are ſuch as altogether ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor repentance; the ſecond are ſuch, as although they acknowledge repentance is needful, and neceſſary for others, yet think that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have no need of it; and the third ſort are ſuch as do confeſs, that repentance is needful even for themſelves, as well as others, but not yet; its time enough here after, there's no ſuch haſte of it. And I hope in the handling of theſe three ſorts of perſons, I ſhall make it appear that reprntance is needful and neceſſary at all times, for all ſorts, Having done this, I ſhall remove ſome lets that hinder men from repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſo give you ſome few Motives to ſtir you up to repentance; and then to wind up all
<pb facs="tcp:151567:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>in a few words of Application.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt of theſe, thoſe that abhor repentance; and they are wilful ſinners, ſuch as go on in ſin, and make it even their trade to ſin: wilful, deſperate, and diſſolute wretches, that laugh at repentance, <hi>who declara their ſin as Sodom did, and hide it not, Iſa. 3.9.</hi> Who will not be brought to abandon their wicked wayes, but go on ſtill in ſwearing and curſing, lying and blaſpheming, whoredome, drunkenneſs, and all uncleanneſs, and that with greedineſs, as the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>Who mock at faith &amp; repentance,</hi> as thoſe ſcoffers did in <hi>2 Pet. 3.4.</hi> Theſe are they, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>2 Pet. 2. That walk after the fleſh in the luſt of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, and count it pleaſure to riot in the day time; whoſe eyes are full of adultery, that cannot ceaſe from ſin: O but the latter end of theſe men is worſe then their beginning.</hi> How many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wretches are there, that live as if they had made a covenant with death and hell, and were at an agréement with the grave, who had rather hazard their ſouls then leave their ſins, who as if there were neither heaven nor hell, run on from one ſin to another. <hi>Come</hi> (ſay they) <hi>we will fetch wine &amp; fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink, and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abundant.</hi> But <hi>Iſa. 56.12. Wo unto them</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>they have rewarded evil to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:151567:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>How little do theſe men think, that God will one day wound the hairy ſcalp of ſuch as go on in ſin: <hi>and that tribulation and wrath, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation &amp; anguiſh, ſhall be upon every ſoul that doth evi, Rom. 2.9.</hi> Let men ſlight repentance never ſo much, a time will come when they ſhal repent, but that too late, even in hell fire for ever. For ſin muſt be repented of, if not on earth, yet in hell; and if you will not loath your companions in ſin here, you ſhal loath them in hell hereafter, you pot-companions, and your harlot companions ſhall loath one another in Hell: then theſe bloody wounds ſhall bleed which you have given your ſouls in the days of your ſollity and pride, and in the times of your deſperate impieties; when nothing but wrath and horrour of conſcience ſhall appear before you, then theſe ſwéet morſels of ſin which have been ſweet as honey to your luſtful appetites, ſhall be vomited up as the bittereſt and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt things in the world. <hi>Conſider this all ye that forget God, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you, Pſal. 50 22.</hi> Be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to forſake your ſins, for ſin and the ſoul muſt part, or elſe hel and the ſoul ſhal meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: <hi>The wicked ſhall be turned into hell, and all the Nations that forget God, Pſalm 9.17.</hi> O that you would ſeriouſly lay theſe things to heart, and now, even now in this your day,
<pb facs="tcp:151567:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>that ye would know the things that belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your everlaſting peace. <hi>To day if you will hear my voice</hi> (ſaith God in the 95. <hi>Pſalm</hi>) <hi>harden not your heart.</hi> Slight not, ſcorn not, reſiſt not the good word of God that invites you to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but break off your ſins by repentance, and turn to God in righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And now for the ſecond ſort, and they are ſuch as think they need no repentance: And they are either ſuch as are morally civil, and honeſt before men, or elſe formal and hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal profeſſors, who ſeem to be, and are not, who profeſs God with their lips, but deny him in their lives; O they have no need of repentance they are no drunkards, nor ſwearers, nor ſuch like: <hi>God I thank thee</hi> (ſaid the proud Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee) <hi>I am not as other men are, extortioners, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, Luke</hi> 18.11. Theſe are ſuch as profeſs God and know much of the mind of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have no need of repentance, they are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of no ſins to repent of: But of theſe it may be ſaid as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid of <hi>Elimas</hi> the ſorcerer, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.10. <hi>That they are full of all ſubtlety, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to all righteouſneſs, who never yet know what ſin meant.</hi> For they that think they have no ſins left to repent of, its a cleer argument that they never yet truly repented themſelves of any one ſin at all, but that they are ſtill in the gall of bitterneſs, and in the bond of iniquity: For
<pb facs="tcp:151567:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>repentance is a continued art, and a grace that muſt have its daily operation, as faith and love muſt continue, ſo muſt repentance; when once the rocky heart of a ſinner is ſmitten by God, the water of repentance will continually flow; ſincere repentants cannot content themſelves with one art or two of repentance, but they muſt daily renew their repentance, for ſin will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, ſo muſt repentance: renewed ſins muſt have renewed Repentance; till we have done ſinning (and that will not be till we have done living) we muſt not have done repenting: if there be a leak in the ſhip, the water muſt be pumpt out, elſe the ſhip is in danger of ſinking; we are leaking veſſels all of us, yea the beſt of us ſin leaks in daily, and is renewed daily, and there muſt be the pump of repentance to carry it out daily, elſe our ſouls will be in danger of ſinking, And for the other ſort who think they need no repentance, they are pure moral honeſt men, who live in a courſe of civility, and take their penny to be as white as any others, theſe are as good as the beſt, and therefore have no need to be any better; they are not deſperately wicked as many are, they are no blaſphemers, nor drunkards, they go to Church and give eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his due, and are loving to their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, and what needs any more. Its true, theſe things are neceſſary, &amp; are required in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian:
<pb facs="tcp:151567:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>but yet civility without ſanctify, at the beſt is but gilded Atheiſm; morality and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vertues are but gilded ſins and gliſtering abominations; the Lord ſeeth many a rotten, baſe, ſtinking heart under a civil coat It civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and morality would have ſerved the turn, then the Phariſees would have gone to heaven before any other; they were civilly honeſt, they were no ſwearers, nor drunkards, they paid tythes, and gave alms, and prayed often; and carried themſelves ſo exact in the world, that it was thought that if but two men in the world ſhould go to heaven, a Scribe ſhould be one, and a Phariſee the other. But what ſaith Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Except your righteouſneſs exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdom if heaven:</hi> And yet their righteouſneſs far exceeded the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all our moral honeſt men. Let a man be never ſo honeſt in outward appearance, let his carriage and behavior be never ſo ſpecious and plauſible in the eyes of the world, let him be never ſo exact ano juſt in his dealings with men, yet if he be not renewed in the ſpirit of his mind, he is never the better for this. If he be not a ſanctified Chriſtian, the word of truth never as yet came home to his ſoul, in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it; he is ſtill in the ſtate of nature, and without God, and as yet far from repentance and ſalvation</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151567:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And then there is a third ſort of impenitents, and they are ſuch as are convinced of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of repentance, but they do not think it a time now to repent: they believe they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, but all in good time, there's no haſte of it yet, it will be time enough hereafter; at the hour of death, when age and ſickneſs is upon them; and they think it a thing of nothing to repent, they can do it when they liſt, its done with a wet finger, there needs no more but to ſay, <hi>Lord have mercy upon me,</hi> when they are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the world, this is the general diſeaſe with which moſt men are infected. But let ſuch men know, that it is a hard matter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, ans ſin is very powerful; and if they do not ſeek to get it ſubdued in the ſtrength of their dayes, it will be too hard for them at the laſt for although men grow weaker and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, yet ſin grows ſtronger and ſtronger; and being as we ſay, bred in the bone, nurſed up by us in our youthful dayes, it will not eaſily be rooted out of the fleſh. <hi>Can the Blackmore change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots? Jer.</hi> 15 23. No they cannot; no more can they that are accuſtomed to do evil, leave it when they liſt.</p>
            <p>If repentance be a thing ſo eaſie, how is it that many who ſought after it could never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it? How many are there that have reared
<pb facs="tcp:151567:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>and cried in the bitterneſs of their ſouls, and in the horror of their conſciences, that they could not repent. <hi>O that I could repent, O that my hard heart would break in pieces!</hi> This hath been the cries of many. It is not in the power of man to repent when he pleaſes, doth God give us ſpace to repent now, it may be he will not do it to morrow: a man by nature as he cannot of himſelf, ſo he hath no inclination of himſelf, to repentance. Repentance its a heart-work, a circumciſing of the heart, and caſting of ſin out of the ſoul, which indeed will make the heart to bleed; which thing no natural man is either willing or able to do. <hi>Mortifie</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Col. 3.5.) your Members which are upon earth;</hi> which thing ſuits not with a natural man. Let no man then put off Repentance, upon ſuch fooliſh wicked thoughts as theſe, that repentance is an eaſie work, which a man may perform when he pleaſes, ſuch ſinful thoughts as theſe will deceive you: Thou that wilt not repent now thou mayeſt, when thou wouldeſt it may be thou ſhalt not be permitted; you that will not repent when God gives ſpace, how juſtly may he when thou wouldeſt deny it thee? becauſe when it was offered to thee thou refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedſt. <hi>Ezek. 24.13. Becauſe I would have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thee, and thou waſt not purged; thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filthineſs, ſaith the Lord.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:151567:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>longer men live in ſin, the ſtronger will ſinne grow in them: he that will not leave ſin when he is yong, will hardly leave it when he is old; it is ſaid of wicked men, in <hi>Job 20.11. Their bones are full of the ſins of their youth, which lie down with them in the duſt.</hi> Not that mens ſins are buried with them in their graves, for then they might be happy, but that they continue with them till death, yea after death. Many a time and often hath the Lord ſtood at the door of mens Conſciences, and knocked to come in, <hi>Rev. 3.20. Behold I ſtand at the door and knock,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) O do not let God wait long, he hath waited a long time already to be gracious unto thee, <hi>Iſa. 30.18.</hi> Do not give the devil the prime and ſtrength of your dayes, and then think to ſerve God in your old age: You do not leave ſin in this, but ſin leaves you; you have not the ſtrength and power to ſin then as you have had, but ſtill your hearts are as bad as ever they were, then put not off your repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance till ſickneſs comes. Happy, yea thrice happy is that man, and bleſſed ſhall he be, that in the time of his youth &amp; health furniſhes his heart and ſoul with comforts againſt the evil day; happy is that ſoul, who when age and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs comes, is ſo ſitted for death by repentance, that when death comes he hath nothing elſe to do but to dye. Be perſwaded th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to repent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,
<pb facs="tcp:151567:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>before you go hence and be no more ſeen; there is no time ours but the preſent time, we do not know whether we ſhall live another day, another night: many that are in health one day are brought to their graves the next. <hi>Our life</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>James) is but a vapour that appeareth for a little time, Jam. 4.14.</hi> we are no ſooner born; but we begin to die. Put not your ſouls off then from day to day, he that's unfit or unwilling to repent to day, will be ſo to morrow; therefore <hi>ſeek the Lord while he may be found, Iſa. 55.6.</hi> There is a time when God will not be found: <hi>Prov. 1.24.</hi> to ver. <hi>30.</hi> ſath God, <hi>Becauſe I called and ye refuſed, and ſet at naught all my counſel, and would none of my reproof; therefore will I laugh at your calamity, and will mock when your fear cometh; when diſtreſs and anguiſh cometh upon you: then ſhall ye call on me, but I will not anſwer; they ſhall ſeek me early, but ſhall not finde me. For that they hated knowledge, and did not chuſe the fear of the Lord; therefore ſhall they eat the fruit of their ways, and be filled with their own devices.</hi> There is a time when mercy may be had, but if we neglect that time, it will not be recovered again though it be ſought for with tears: there is a time, when with the wiſe Vigins we may enter into the wedding, but if we take not that time, we may with the fooliſh ones have the door ſhut againſt us, <hi>Mat. 25.</hi> Then may we knock
<pb facs="tcp:151567:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>and call, yea, cry, <hi>Lord, Lord, open to us:</hi> but the Lord ſhall ſay unto us, <hi>I know you not.</hi> The old world had a long time of Repentance, a hundred and twenty years did <hi>Noah</hi> preach re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to them, and yet they repented not: but the <hi>Ninivites</hi> they had but a ſhort time given them, but forty dayes, and yet they repented: they made the Day of Repentance whilſt the Sun of Gods patience ſhined upon them.</p>
            <p>God is not bound to wait mens leaſure, the Soul is but a tenant at will, and may ſuddenly be turned out of doors, and when you lie upon your ſick beds, the Lord may fill your hearts with ſuch fears as may make your conſciences altogether deſpair of mercy. God ſent you his ſervants early and late, in ſeaſon &amp; out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to invite you to repent, but you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent you ſay hereafter, you will if you can, you hope God will work it in you. What ground have you of this hope? hath God made you any ſuch promiſe? Thou canſt not draw out the thred of thy life one minute, for ought thou knoweſt this may be thy laſt day; the tenders of mercy, and the offers of grace are at an end when thy life ends, if not before: you know that time and tide ſtayes no mans leaſure, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is ſo wiſe as to take time and tide for worldly affairs; will any man be ſo ſottiſh as to defer the time of his ſowing till harveſt? men
<pb facs="tcp:151567:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>will not be carrying out of dung, when they ſhould be fetching in of Corn: no, they will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch thoſe things firſt which are of moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. And is there any thing of more neceſſity then the ſalvation of your ſouls? will your ſouls be ſaved without repentance? or can you repent when you will? but you will ſay, you are young, and therefore may be born with a while, which is the Devils divinity; for young men have no more liberty allowed them to ſin or to put off repentance, then old men have, its the Devils policy to infuſe this into thy brains, that he may enſnare thee. It was the commendation of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy, that from a Childe he had known the holy Scriptures, 1 Tim. 1.</hi> Young Saints, ſay ſome, but not the word of God, prove old Devils, But I am ſure it is a rare thing to ſée and old ſinner to become a young Saint, When the devil and ſin hath lorded it in your ſoul, yea tyrannized both over ſoul &amp; body, for thirty or forty years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, do you think then that a little groaning or crying, <hi>Lord have mercy upon me,</hi> wil be able to diſpoſſeſs him at the laſt, he having gotten too ſtrong a footing in your ſoul to be beaten out of his quarters ſo eaſily; he that will not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber God when he is young and living, its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be feared God will be unmindeful of him when he is old and dying. Therefore once more I beſeech you in the bowels of Chriſt, ſpeedily
<pb facs="tcp:151567:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſet about the work of repentance, leſt when it is too late you repent, weep, and mourn, that you repented not before. Do not ſay of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as <hi>Felix</hi> ſpake to <hi>Paul, Thou wilt repent when thou art better at leaſure, another time ſhall ſerve the turn:</hi> it may be thou mayeſt not live to another time, or if thou doeſt, thy heart may then be as hard, if not harder then now it is, Would you not in the day of the Lord be in a worſe condition then heathens or infidels are? Then repent. Would you not when you are dead be in a worſe condition then toads or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents? then repent.</p>
            <p>It may be ſaid of every impenitent ſinner, as Chriſt ſaid of <hi>Judas</hi> in the <hi>26.</hi> of <hi>Matthew,</hi> and the <hi>24.</hi> ver. <hi>It had been good for that man if he had never been born.</hi> Heathens in the day of Judgement ſhall be in a better condition then impenitent Chriſtians, for they ſhall have the leſſer condemnation, becauſe of their ignorance; who it may be would have done better if they had known more. <hi>It ſhall be more tollerable</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>for Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgement, then for thou Capernaum:</hi> Thou <hi>England</hi> that art exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to heaven in Goſpel-mercies, take heed and beware leſt thou be not thrown down to hell in Goſpel-vengeance.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now ſhew you the lets that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:151567:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>men from Repentance, and ſo endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to remove them; but I ſhall onely name them, and ſo conclude with ſome few motivhs to ſtir you up to Repentance. Now the lets that keep men off from Repentance, are either from Sin and Satan, or elſe from our ſelves and the World; the Devil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades men that repentance is a needleſs work and men need not trouble themſelves with it, for thoſe that God hath ordained to live ſhall be ſaved, let them live never ſo looſely; and thoſe that he hath appointed to wrath ſhall be damned, let them repent never ſo much. But to remove this let out of the way, know this, that all thoſe, that God hath ordained to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhall firſt or laſt, more or leſs, be brought to embrace the means. In the <hi>13.</hi> of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the <hi>48. As many as were ordained to eternal life, believed.</hi> God hath joyned the end and the means together, and curſed is he that dares to ſeparate them: Salvation without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is impoſſible; <hi>without holineſs no man ſhall ſee God, Heb. 5.19.</hi> A ſecond way by which the Devil keeps men off from Repentance, is Gods mercy; God is merciful, ſaith the devil, his mercy is over all his works, &amp; he that made you will not damn you, you need not to fear it: True it is, even to wicked men God is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; but theſe are but mercies on the left hand,
<pb facs="tcp:151567:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>common mercies; its a mercy to men that they live, its a mercy that we were not born mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and its a mercy to have outward enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but what are theſe to the peculiar mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God? It was a good ſpeech of a godly man, ſaith he, He that made thee without thee, will not ſave thee without thee; if thou art in a ditch and wilt do no more to come out but cry, God help me, thou mayeſt lie and periſh. O do not dare to go on in ſin, becaus God is merciful; <hi>Shall we ſin</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that grace may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound? no, God forbid.</hi> I dare not ſaith a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious heart: If ever you would partake of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, you muſt depart from iniquity, <hi>2 Tim. 2.19. Let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity.</hi> I dare holdly ſay, that if all the clouds of heaven ſhould continually ſhowre down mercy, there would not ſo much as one drop fall upon any impenitent perſon.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the devil labours to keep men off from repentance, by bringing them to deſpair of mercy, if he cannot work men into preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption by the conſideration of Gods mercies, he will do what he can to bring thent into deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by telling them that mercy is out of date. But let not this hinder thy repentance, for as it cannot be too ſoon to repent, ſo its never too late to repent, better once then never. I do not ſpeak this that any ſhould neglect to repent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,
<pb facs="tcp:151567:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>but that none ſhould ever deſpair of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and thereby be hindred from this duty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, A ſecond let that hinders repentance, is the world, the luſts of the fleſh, and the pride of life, the pleaſures and preferments of the world: theſe fight againſt the ſpirit, and reſiſt the work of repentance: Voluptouſneſs and Drunkenneſs unfits men for repentance, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe muſt be abſtained front <hi>(1 Pet. 2. 11.) as things that war againſt the ſoul. Mortifie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>your members which are upon earth, fornication, uncleanneſs, &amp;c. Col. 3.5.</hi> Theſe muſt be mortified. And then a third let that keeps men from repentance is ſin, ſin hath ſuch a commanding power over the ſouls of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerated perſons, <hi>So that</hi> (as it is <hi>Rom. 6.10.) they give themſelves over as ſervants to ſin, and to uncleanneſs.</hi> O then for the Lords ſake, avoid all occaſions of ſin; <hi>Let not ſin therefore reign in your mortal bodies, that you ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof: neither yield you your mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as inſtruments of unrighteouſneſs unto ſin, but yield your ſelves unto God, as inſtruments of righteouſneſs, Rom. 6.12, 13. verſes.</hi> O that I could prevail with you, and that the Lord would perſwade your hearts of the dreadful &amp; doleful condition of all umpenitent Sinners. Conſider then I beſeech you in the fear of the Lord theſe following conſiderations; and firſt
<pb facs="tcp:151567:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>of all know this, you that live in the love of ſin you live in the hatred of God; for the love of God and the love of ſin cannot poſſibly dwell together, and they that dwell in it ſhall never dwell with God, <hi>Pſal. 15.</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Lord, who ſhall abide in thy Tabernacle, who ſhall dwell in thy holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ill? He that walketh uprightly, and worketh righteouſneſs.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>1 Cor. 6.9. Know ye not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God? Be not deceived, neither fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abuſers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with mankinde, nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> And <hi>Pſalm 97. Ye that love the Lord hate evil.</hi> Alſo <hi>2 Tim. 2.19. Let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity.</hi> Secondly, all thoſe that ſin, or are under the power and command of ſin, are of the dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>For he that commits ſin (ſaith St. John) is of the devil, John 3.9.</hi> And is it not a ſad thing to be und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the power of the Devil? Every wicked man is the Devils ſtave, and be doth the devils drudgery: where ever ſin is, in the love of it, there is alſo the devil; the devil keeps court in wicked mens hearts. Thirdly, ſin is the high way to deſtruction, <hi>Is not deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the wicked?</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, Chap. 31.3.</hi> Yes, that it is, <hi>And a ſtrange puniſhment to the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb facs="tcp:151567:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>of iniquity.</hi> Fourthly and laſtly, ſin brought wrath and condemnation upon the ſoul: <hi>If ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall die, Rom. 8.13. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhall be turned into hell, and all the Nations that forget God, Pſal. 9.17.</hi> Theſe things being conſidered &amp; ſeriouſly taken to heart, methinks ſhould not onely awaken ſinners out of their ſléepy ſecurity, but alſo provoke them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And then there is another let which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders men from repentance, and that is in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which is of all other the greateſt let; for did not our own baſe hearts deceive us, the devil the world, and ſin, could never hinder us from coming to
<pb facs="tcp:151567:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>God by repentance; &amp; theſe lets from ourſelves are either from ignorance or hardnes of heart, <hi>Eph 4.18. Men,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>through the ignorance that is in them, &amp; through the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their hearts being paſt feeling, have given themſelves over unto laſciviouſneſs, &amp; to work all uncleannes with greedines.</hi> Ignorance muſt néeds be a great let to repentance, no wonder when men know not the danger of ſin, nor the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of repentance, that they live in ſin and never come to repentance; who is there that ſéeks for that he knoweth not of? If impenitent ſinners did but know what a dangerous condition they were in without repentance, they would never ſuffer their eyes to ſléep, nor their eye-lids to ſlumber, before they had made their peace with, God by repentance: O then for the Lords ſake get acquaintance with God, <hi>and learn to know what an odious thing ſin is, Job 22.21.</hi> Acquaint now thy ſelf with God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be at peace, thereby good ſhall come unto thee, thereby thou maiſt be brought to repentance. Then ſecondly, there's in us hardneſs of heart, which hinders the work of repentance: It is ſaid <hi>of Zedekiah, 2 Chron. 36.13. That he hardned his heart that he might not return to the Lord his God.</hi> And this hardneſs of heart is very lamentable, becauſe all the means which God uſes to ſoften, work not upon it at all; <hi>And Pharaoh hardened his heart, and would not let the children of Iſrael go, Ex. 8.32.</hi> All the ſore judgements of God upon him could not prevail with his hard heart, he would not let them go; ſo wicked men whoſe hearts are hardened, they will not let their ſins go, neither the judgement, nor the mercies of God will prevail with wicked men, to turn them from their ſins. <hi>Amos 4 12.</hi> ſaith God, <hi>Though I have ſent among you judgment upon judgment, plague, famine, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſom beaſts, yet have you not retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto me.</hi> Therefore I beſeech you, in love to your poor ſouls, that by prayer you would beg of God to give you ſoftned hearts, that may melt &amp; tremble at the word of God, leſt by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on in your ſins, ye bring upon your ſolves ſwiſt deſtrution. And ſo I come to give you
<pb facs="tcp:151567:21"/>ſome means and motives to ſtir you up to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and I ſhall conclude.</p>
            <p>The firſt and principal means of workin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> repentance where it is not, is the word of God <hi>Mat. 4.17. And Jeſus began to preach, and to ſay Repent, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand</hi> Chriſts friſt Sermon was a Sermon of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, therefore if ever you would repent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your ſins, attend upon the word of God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a woful ſad condition are thoſe in that want th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> word of God: What the Preacher ſaid, <hi>Eccle 11.6. In the morning</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſowe thy ſeed, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the evening withhold not thy hand;</hi> ſo ſay I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hearing the word of God; Hear it in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hear it in the afternoon; hear it on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lords day, and hear it in the week day, take a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> opprotunities of hearing the word of God.</p>
            <p>And then a ſecond help is, to conſider th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> goodneſs and power of God, his almighty, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his all ſéeing eye; conſider God ſées and know and thy wayes, and is able to puniſh thée for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy ſins, if men were but convinced of this truth, they durſt not ſin ſo boldly as they do But I paſs by this to give you ſome few Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of the truth of repentance, and they ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brieſly theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſoul that hath truly repented is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry careful to avoid even the occaſion of ſin, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> keeps himſelf at a diſtance bath from ſin &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;
<pb facs="tcp:151567:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>he will diſpenſe with no ſin at all, but wil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y as <hi>Ephraim</hi> did, <hi>What have I to do any more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith ſin?</hi> And ſecondly, he that is truly turned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ont ſin unto God, will endeavour to turn thers alſo: he is not content that he himſelf is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urned to God, but he will draw others to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo. Thirdly, he that hath truly repented is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y careful tofurniſh himſelf againſt the aſſaults of the devil; <hi>Thy word</hi> (ſaith <hi>David, Pſ. 119.11.) have I hid in my heart, that I might not ſin againſt thee.</hi> A true repentant treaſures up the word of God in his heart, <hi>and walks worthy of the Lord unto all well-pleaſing, being fruitful unto every good work, and encreaſing in the knowledge of God, Col. 1.10.</hi> They do it, as it is in <hi>Pſ. 110.23. They keep the teſtimonies of God, and ſeek him with their whole heart;</hi> they alſo do no iniquity, they walk in his ways. <hi>Their delight is in the law of God, and in his law they do meditate day and night, Pſal. 1.2.</hi> Fourthly, he that hath truly repented, is full of holy indignation againſt ſin, and turns ſin quite out of doors, he cannot endure the ſight of it. Fifthly, he that hath truly repented, is full of fear, he is filled with an awful, reverencial, and filial fear of the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of God, and he is afraid of diſpleaſing God by ſin, Sirthly, a true penitent is full of holy and heavenly deſires; he deſires more of God, and more acquaitance with the wayes of God,
<pb facs="tcp:151567:22"/>more communion with God in Ordinances Seventhly, true penitents are very zealous fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God: <hi>O how do I love thy law,</hi> ſaith <hi>David</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>119. Pſalm.</hi> A godly man cannot endure t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſee God diſhonoured; as it is ſaid of <hi>Lot</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecond of <hi>Peter 2.8. He vexed his righteous ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from day to day with their unlawful deeds.</hi> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then laſtly, where true repentance is wrought it will work a holy change in the ſoul; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereas ſin was formerly delighted in, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true Penitent hath it in indignation; they will not onely turn ſin out of doors, but alſo are ready to cut it in pieces as it were: true peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents have a feeling on their hearts for ſin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will loath themſelvs for the evil of their ways. It is a hard thing for a man to loath himſelf, every man naturally loves himſelf, but true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents loath and abhor themſelves, as <hi>Job</hi> did. A repentant eye ſees matter enough in himſelf of ſelf-abhorrency: Repentance lets us ſee what black deſiled creatures we are by nature, <hi>Ezek. 20.43. You ſhall remember your wayes,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and ſhall loath your ſelves in your own ſight.</hi> And ſo much for the Evidences of repentance.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo then, that repentance is ſo abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, an that there is a great danger in putting it off from day to day; and that a ſick bed repentance is no repentance, or
<pb facs="tcp:151567:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>at moſt but a ſickly Repentance, how highly then doth it concern every one of us, even to day, while it is called to day, to begin our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and not onely to begin, but to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in it to the end of our dayes: Let the time paſt of our lives ſuffice us to have wrought our own wills, and to have walked in our own wayes, and ley us reſolve for the time to come to live unto God, and be not weary, for in due ſeaſon thou ſhalt reap if thou faint not. Make repentance thy daily work, that ſo thy peace may be made with God, and when thou comeſt to dye, thou mayeſt have nothing elſe to do but to dye. He that labours not to kill ſin by repentance in his life, will be very unfit to die when death comes, death is onely welcome to a gracious penitent ſoul; they are not fit to die, in whom ſin is not killed by Repentance; they have done nothing of that work which God ſent them into the world to do, that have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented: repentance ſweetens our lives, and takes away the bitterneſs of death, and onely to penitent ſinners is mercy promiſed. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der there is an abſolute neceſſity of repentance, we cannot be ſaved unleſs we repent; <hi>Except ye repent</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ye ſhall all likewiſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, Luke 13.3.</hi> Conſider alſo thy life is but ſhort: thou haſt but a littlé time to live in the world, thou haſt need to beſtir thy ſelf then, and
<pb facs="tcp:151567:23"/>to husband thy time to the beſt advantage thy ſoul; thy precious and immortal ſoul w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be in danger of hell fire, if thou repent not: no repentance, no ſalvation; and if thou do not repent thee here of thy ſins, thou wilt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thy coſt repent thee hereafter in hell f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the neglect of repentance; thou wilt then cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the day wherein thou didſt deſpiſe repentanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then if there be any love in thée to thy precio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſoul, whatever thou doeſt, repent. Conſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> alſo the end, for which Chriſt came into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> world: <hi>Mat. 9.13. I came</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſinners to repentance.</hi> Be zealous therefore an repent, and as <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Mat. 3.8. Let us a labour to bring forth fruits meet for repentanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Now the Lord work theſe truths upon you hearts, and the Lord give every one of us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto life, repentance never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of: Which the Lord of hi infinite mercy grant unto us all. To whom be glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and honour for ever. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:151567:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A ſhort Motive to Repentance.</head>
            <l>THe Glaſs doth run, the Clock doth go,</l>
            <l>Awake from ſin, why ſleep you ſo:</l>
            <l>In ſin ſleep not ſecurely ſtill,</l>
            <l>Leſt thou by ſin thy ſoul doeſt kill:</l>
            <l>While thou haſt time do not delay,</l>
            <l>Defer not off from day to day;</l>
            <l>Thou art not ſure to tarry here,</l>
            <l>No not one quarter of a year;</l>
            <l>No not one week, nor yet one day,</l>
            <l>One hour thou art not ſure to ſtay;</l>
            <l>Thou haſt not ſpace in thine own power,</l>
            <l>To live one minute of an hour:</l>
            <l>The preſent time ſee then thou take,</l>
            <l>Thy peace with God in Chriſt to make.</l>
            <l>Keep Faith and true Repentance ſtill,</l>
            <l>And then ley Death come when it will.</l>
            <l>Thou art prepared for to dye;</l>
            <l>And thou ſhalt live eternally.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151567:24"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader,</head>
            <p>There is lately publiſhed an excellent an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> profitable Sermon, called, The Chriſtian bleſſed Choice. Likewiſe Chriſts firſt Sermon. Alſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſts laſt Sermon. And the Chriſtians beſt Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Alſo Heavens Glory, and Hells Horro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> And the School of Grace. Alſo, Awarning-piec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Sloathful, Idle, Careleſs, Drunken, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Ones of theſe laſt and worſt of times. Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> godly Books, and are but three pence price.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe,
<list>
                  <item>1. Englands Faithful Phyſician.</item>
                  <item>2. Dooms-day at hand.</item>
                  <item>3. The dreadful character of a drunkard.</item>
                  <item>4. The Fathers laſt Bleſſing to his children.</item>
                  <item>5. The ſin of Pride arraigned and condemned</item>
                  <item>6. The Plain Mans Plain Path-way to Heaven</item>
                  <item>7. The Black Book of Conſcience.</item>
                  <item>8. Peters Sermon of Repentance.</item>
                  <item>9. The Charitable Chriſtian.</item>
                  <item>10. Death Triumphant.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All very neceſſary for theſe licentious times, and each of them being but of two pence price. They are to be ſold by <hi>Elizabeth Andrews,</hi> at the White Lion near <hi>Pye-Corner.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
